[SPEAKER_02]: So, I thought we could discuss the importance of faith in practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why, for example, it's the first of the five faculties, the faculties of the Noble Disciple that the Buddha described.
[SPEAKER_02]: The first one is faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, in many occasions, it's said that
[SPEAKER_02]: yonison manasikāra, which the Buddha said is the condition for the arising of the right view, it depends on faith as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: So... and, eh... because, you know, there's there's a certain sort of tendency, especially when Buddhism came to the West, where it's thought of as like a
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not really something you have to accept.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's more like something that you take it or leave it, depending on whether it resonates with your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, only the parts that resonate with you, and that seem true to you, you accept.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, the rest, you can not consider it part of Buddhism, if you want.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can you can pick and choose from within the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, definitely there would be some benefit to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, to whichever extent the person adopts it, it would be beneficial.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's a different question now to say whether it's possible to attain the right view based on such an attitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, we can start by
[SPEAKER_02]: Contemplating, reflecting on how would a lack of faith obstruct not all practice, but, let's say, sufficient practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: How does lack of faith obstruct the practice
[SPEAKER_02]: And, or, more acutely, before we even go into that, what is faith?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because we... some people might hear that word and might confuse it with the faith of faith in God or something like that, faith in Christianity.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there are some overlaps, but they shouldn't be thought of as exactly the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we could clarify that first, like, what is faith?
[SPEAKER_01]: This is something that I thought was interesting there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think in a few suttas, it talks about
[SPEAKER_01]: Kind of discussions among householders in the Buddhist time, and specifically when they would speak about other householders who were basically that they kind of held in low esteem.
[SPEAKER_01]: One of the things that they would often say is like, so and so is faithless.
[SPEAKER_01]: He does not have faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, to me, that was interesting, because that kind of... it wasn't faith in something specific.
[SPEAKER_01]: It almost seemed like it was pointing to a specific type of attitude that could be brought towards different things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, could you...
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess, could a person who is
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeking some kind of... basically, somebody who's beginning a noble search, have faith, even if it's not... Could they have the attitude of faith, even if there's not yet something that they're kind of putting it into, I guess, is the question.
[SPEAKER_01]: And my thought is, it would kind of have to be that attitude of, like, admitting you don't know, and
[SPEAKER_04]: Being open to the fact that somebody may know.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which already presupposes that you have acknowledged that there's a problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right?
[SPEAKER_04]: If you don't recognize that the house is on fire, then you wouldn't make any move to get out.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you wouldn't feel that there is a need.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't see any value.
[SPEAKER_02]: in somebody who knows how to put out the fire because you think the house isn't on fire.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it begins by having some recognition that there is suffering, which is actually in that same sutta which says that
[SPEAKER_04]: yoniso, manasikāra, depends on faith, but what does this faith depend upon?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's another one, but it does say... there's definitely... the statement says suffering is what gives rise to faith.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, this is what I was trying to get at.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, somebody needs to have recognized that having been born is not one big party, but actually fairly problematic to begin with.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, they need to be honest about that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, the faith arises, like, you know, even the Buddha, who did not find, in the end, a teacher that showed him fully the way out, but even he had that faith, like, an escape from all this must be possible, because otherwise, this is just a doomed situation, which he did not accept.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is, in essence, it seems to me, what faith is like.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not worthwhile going on with any of this.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there has to be a way out.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is the basic attitude, it seems to me, of faith.
[SPEAKER_04]: At least, how it starts.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, once you have
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's, eh... That, that, the component of faith is what enables you to
[SPEAKER_02]: Push beyond what you... your current situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Put it that way, because... Actually, it's... it's even part of that mundane, quote-unquote, mundane right view, that this is to talk about, that says, there is a mother, there is father, there is given, there is a result of action, and at the end it says,
[SPEAKER_02]: There are ascetics and brahmins who have understood understood this world and the next.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, that's already one... something that, you know, for many might be hard to accept.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like that...
[SPEAKER_02]: It isn't just a kind of subjective... sort of everybody has their own interpretation and it's kind of... nothing... it doesn't really matter in the end.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereas, no, it says mundane right view is at least being open to the possibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: That some people have actually rightly understood, that there is such a thing as right understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what would, first of all, open you up to the possibility as well, that your present understanding is the reason why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why, then, faith comes before wisdom, even, because... even for the five faculties of a noble disciple, because that faith keeps that kind of... keeps you questioning yourself, because you see that there's something...
[SPEAKER_02]: Ahead of you, kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even the Buddha said, when he, I think, shortly after his awakening, he said, well, I don't have any teacher, I haven't learned this from anyone, but you shouldn't live without respecting something.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then he said, well, I will then respect the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's another thing that's quite connected with faith, that sense of respect.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it shouldn't be confused with, which is what I was sort of getting into before, it shouldn't be confused with
[SPEAKER_02]: piety, which is kind of the more usual conception of faith, which is often kind of what you see in Buddhist countries.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's kind of just a blind performance of certain observances.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when it comes to like, well, am I seeing this as valuable in the context of changing my behaviors and my actions,
[SPEAKER_02]: In daily life, that aspect is something that's more hard to find, that somebody has that attitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that is more of a... like, you could put it that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Actual faith needs to have an effect on your actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it doesn't, if it's just a belief... Well, yeah, that's what it would be.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would just be a belief.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not what faith really is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Faith should be connected with a sense of something that needs to be done, not just a empty conviction that you proclaim the Buddha is the best, but you don't live to align yourself with those values.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... Yeah, so to get the motivation that there is a
[SPEAKER_00]: Also, without experimenting it by oneself in the moment, but there is a way which is... which has been experimented and also fulfilled by other sage-wise people, and so this thing in the motivation is to keep in mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, yes, because...
[SPEAKER_02]: There has to be that quality of basically realizing how deep wrong view goes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's kind of a... Oftentimes, people don't have that recognition.
[SPEAKER_02]: They think, oh, sometimes,
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I am ignorant, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, sometimes I fall off the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, it's a much more broad...
[SPEAKER_02]: Without faith, you won't be going to the root.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it says, without faith, you cannot have yonisonmanasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will not go to the source of your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, because there's always layers and layers and layers.
[SPEAKER_02]: of assumptions, of questioning, things that you don't question, things that you take for granted, tendencies that are just purely based on craving, on getting pleasure and avoiding pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even when, you know, things that might seem justified in the context of dhamma, like, you know, I don't know, helping people in the monastery or something, and then
[SPEAKER_02]: You kind of... if you don't have enough faith, and you see... well, clearly, the Buddha said, being engaged with distractions, and he even spoke about that, like a monk who spends his time distracted, he's not progressing in the practice, but then, if you don't have enough faith, it's not necessarily that you would think like, oh, that's wrong or something, but you wouldn't kind of
[SPEAKER_02]: Snap out of it with enough strength to see, wait, I am actually falling into this.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's a very coarse example, but it's to the whole range of all the factors of the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_02]: In order to acquire those factors, you need to be willing to accept
[SPEAKER_02]: Wait, but my view might be wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: My intention might be wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: My speech might be wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: At any given time, if you have faith in the Buddha, in the practical sense, you would be willing to accept that maybe you, sure, you're better than before, but there's still more.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's really that purpose of faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's another thing that I think people often overlook, is that
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, there's often the descriptions of stream-entry as, sure, understanding the Four Noble Truths and all those things, but, you know, many people can say that they understand things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's kind of a very...
[SPEAKER_02]: In the end, it's not necessarily a very reliable criteria, but
[SPEAKER_02]: What they also say, more acutely than understanding, in the suttas, as the factors of stream-entry, is that unshakable faith, or absolute faith, in the Buddha, Dhamma, Saṅgha, which isn't... sometimes... see, that's a kind of a...
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a fine line to thread there, because it says there that they also are independent of the teacher.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, see, it's not the same type of faith of, like, you know, hugging, just constantly hugging the legs of the teacher, and just going wherever they tell you to go, and not having a mind of your own.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, there's no blind obedience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But at the same time, it is unshakable faith to the point where, you know, it's also said that that's what would allow a community of people to live together in harmony, which is the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: In that sense, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: And you have that other sutta where these three monks were saying together, and they say... sometimes they would have an idea about something, and then they would say, oh, but why shouldn't I do what these other venerables want to do?
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, that's kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: But see, you cannot get that by like, okay, now let me just not have preferences.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me just pretend that I go along with what everybody else does.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's a by-product.
[SPEAKER_02]: of the right understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's more like an indication, let's say, that you have understood things properly, but it's not about fabricating a sense of just blind obedience to seniors or blind obedience to whoever you take as a teacher.
[SPEAKER_02]: It should be more like, okay, but
[SPEAKER_02]: I think I understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, but now do I have that unshakable confidence and faith whereby, basically, I'm ready to, at any time, revise my understanding?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, can we say that faith is that quality or faculty that prevents you from stagnating, but you keep digging deeper until there is no doubt?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that is, right, because in other traditions there might be an attitude like somebody suffers from doubt, and then you say, don't doubt, believe.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right?
[SPEAKER_04]: And then the belief becomes the sort of the opposite of the doubt.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what we are saying here, it seems to me, is, no, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: Cultivate doubt, because you have faith that there is more to be understood.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which is quite a different take on what faith is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's... faith would have to... faith is what would allow you to admit that you're still subject to doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because... that, like you said, it will make you push far enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will make you dig deep enough.
[SPEAKER_04]: Until you find that which cannot be doubted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and then you have...
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you have...
[SPEAKER_02]: Automatically, when you don't have faith in something, you have faith in yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: That doesn't take like a conscious effort.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or faith in your views, let's say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Faith in whatever you happen to be in your current kind of situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, in order to make progress, you need to have faith in something other than yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like that's, at least in the context of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, even actually in mundane terms, like, if somebody's taking a treatment from a doctor, and they have more faith in what they think is the right thing to do about that illness, and then the doctor tells them, well,
[SPEAKER_02]: You're supposed to wake up at 2 a.m. and take this pill.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't take it at any other time of the day.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only at 2 a.m.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if they think they know better, they will take it whenever it's more convenient or not take it at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: And because of that, they won't get cured.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not necessarily a kind of conscious choice that I choose to be faithless.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just by not, let's say, considering that direction, or the importance of that direction, and most importantly, by not seeing the predicament that you find yourself in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if the person also doesn't feel that the sickness that they have is such a big deal,
[SPEAKER_02]: They might, you know, have... sure, they have... they believe that this doctor knows what he's talking about, but if they don't really feel that sense of urgency to cure themselves, then that also will lead to the lack of faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the proper sense, as I just said, faith that leads to... that affects your actions, not just your beliefs.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, actions and your beliefs, plus the cure is not necessarily pleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, in order... Well, yeah, waking up at 2 a.m. is not... Yeah, so, in order to sustain the right practice, which is not necessarily pleasant, there needs to be the faith which is gonna bridge that gap, because that faith is saying, no, no, that this pleasure that you now suffer from, that can eventually disappear, if you stick to this.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there is a... there is somewhat of a relation, particularly in the beginning, between faith and time.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, the only pleasure you know is sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's painful.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't know anything else.
[SPEAKER_04]: But there is the faith that it is still worthwhile to restrain those sensual pleasures, because to be free from that is more peaceful, even though that peace you
[SPEAKER_02]: And of course, again, it cannot be like I just decide to have this belief that it's possible to be free from sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to have seen the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of your current situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the only way that the faith has that proper footing.
[SPEAKER_02]: As we said, that depends on suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Recognizing suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's also that sutta that says, what's the result of suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: It says, either madness or vexation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or a noble search.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that noble search is basically exactly that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It says, actually the description says, who knows
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, that's right, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's exactly then, when the faith gains a basis, where you recognize the conundrum that you're in.
[SPEAKER_02]: There was even one sutta I came across recently that said that there are things that are unpleasant to do, but have a pleasant... unpleasant to do, but have an unpleasant result.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pleasant to do, that have a pleasant result.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unpleasant to do, that have a pleasant result.
[SPEAKER_02]: And pleasant to do, that have an unpleasant result.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, it says, how do you tell apart the wise from the fool?
[SPEAKER_02]: And it says it's because, you know, even when you tell the fool, don't do the thing that's pleasant to do, but leads to unpleasant results, he will still do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you tell him to do the thing that's unpleasant to do, but leads to pleasant results, he won't do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the opposite for the wise person.
[SPEAKER_04]: In other words, the fool is concerned with immediate pleasure only.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because he doesn't have faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because he doesn't recognize the... yeah, like I've been saying, that he needs to get out of this situation that he finds himself in.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's really where the dhamma applies.
[SPEAKER_02]: The dhamma isn't supposed to be
[SPEAKER_02]: Like a public teaching for everyone in the world...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, sure, if people can... everyone could keep the five precepts, but that's not specifically what the dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_02]: The dhamma is for people who recognize an issue with their current way of being.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the existence, basically, in the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is where faith begins.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, the suttas as well define that there's various formulations of these five faculties, but one of them also includes the sense of fear, sorry, sense of shame and fear of wrongdoing, which also depend on faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, see,
[SPEAKER_02]: Oftentimes, you know, there are things that seem pretty harmless, that people might not think are a big deal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, some people don't think killing mosquito is a big deal, or drinking alcohol from time to time is a big deal.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that sense of shame and fear of wrongdoing, which is, in regard to unwholesome states, which is one of the the powers of a noble disciple, like, that depends on faith, in the sense that, no, it doesn't matter how
[SPEAKER_02]: That I, right now, think that this doesn't seem like a big deal, because I know that I'm still subject to ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in other words, I put the dhamma first.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know that, okay, if the Buddha said this, and I am claiming to be aiming for the same goal that the Buddha taught, then I cannot, honestly, at the same time, say, like, I am applying the treatment,
[SPEAKER_02]: But at the same time...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think I know better.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, eh... Yeah, this comes then back to what we said at the very beginning, this attitude of picking and choosing what you like from the discourses.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's going to be a problem to the degree that one has been developing faith, because the dhamma is... it's one vision, it's one teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, this attitude of picking and choosing is only possible when there is some lack of faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then also,
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course, the tendency will be to reject the things that you should have the most sense of urgency to accept, because that's where the wrong views are going to be most strongly established.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because there's a natural tendency to not want to be disturbed and to be, let's say, peaceful, whereas actually, if you want to uproot
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, like I said, unpleasant now, but... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, against the grain also depends on faith.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, why would you go against the grain if you don't have faith that in the long run it's worthwhile?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the phrase.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, as the Buddha said, the dhamma goes against the grain or against the stream.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, only if you know that there is something better at the top of the stream, you have faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, everything else is going to be convincing you.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, actually, I should just keep going, because why would I just try to swim against... See, everybody else is just going down there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why am I the only one who's swimming back up?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So...
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but that's a very inauthentic way of regarding things, because you are already giving more authority to the group or to what everybody else is doing.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if the Buddha was thinking like that, he would never have become the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the thing is, these pressures and these tendencies of your mind,
[SPEAKER_02]: They might still be there, but again, faith is what allows you to go against it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereas if you don't have the faith as a grounding, you just go with whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even the wisdom as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's common to have, especially Westerners, to have a very kind of intellectual, analytical approach.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if then... it's not that that's bad necessarily, but then if the faith gets sort of pushed away,
[SPEAKER_02]: And not seen as important, then, eh... ignorance, fundamentally, is like... infects the whole of your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so those... the concepts and... and ideas that you... that you might be operating with, yes, you need to improve them and... and upgrade them, but if that's all you rely on, eh... fundamentally, ignorance will still be, eh... sort of running the show.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereas faith is kind of that outside sort of input, the utterance of another, kind of that outside input that, okay, yes, I have to understand it for myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not just about agreeing with all that what this person says, but I put the teaching first, at least while I'm trying to develop it, I put the teaching first and then my reasoning second.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what I was going to say is that's actually one of the
[SPEAKER_02]: There are better ways to, regardless of what teacher you follow, it would actually be much more of an authentic and sincere way of going about it, to have that recognition of
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, if I have any chance of actually, you know, getting the right view and abandoning ignorance, I have to commit myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I can't be picking and choosing, because that's... Like, imagine just a doctor who says, oh, well, you got to take these pills, and there might be other pills that will have, you know, what's it called?
[SPEAKER_04]: Similar effect?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, like, they will sort of nullify the effects of these ones that you're taking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, the person goes to the other doctor, who prescribes them exactly those pills, and then, you know, they're taking both at the same time, and how will they know that which of the two doctors was actually... like, they have no way to know whether both of them were wrong,
[SPEAKER_02]: Or whether one of them was wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or whether both of them was wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's better to commit to one teaching fully, even if it then turns out to be a wrong teaching at some point, at least you can then say with certainty, this didn't work.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's what the Buddha did, actually.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then your noble search continues.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, if you have, like, several teachers and you don't see contradictions between those teachings... Or you do, but you kind of just...
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, you pick and choose in order to make it somewhat coherent according to your own standards.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, you can pursue that for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if it doesn't bring any results, you will not be in a position to now find out what was actually beneficial and what wasn't.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's not a very popular approach these days.
[SPEAKER_04]: Most of the time, a sort of open-mindedness is what people, you know, seem to prefer, rather than to just stick to one thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: But actually, that is probably a shortcoming, as we are now discussing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and it's not a then-about, because you do have that sutta where the Buddha says, how do you preserve the truth?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you guard the truth?
[SPEAKER_02]: And it says, until you've seen it for yourself, you shouldn't be talking as if, you know, this is certain, this...
[SPEAKER_02]: I know this for sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, at the same time, you do have a sense of, well, right now, this is what I am applying myself to.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, everything else, for now, because I developed enough faith, I investigated, as Aṭṭhuta says, you visit the teacher, ask questions, investigate, ponder, reflect, then faith arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you have a sense of
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, this is actually worthwhile committing to.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, at least for that duration, if you have a... in order to have a real chance of... of... being able to judge for yourself whether that teaching was truly right or wrong, you need to actually apply it in that sort of focused sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what the Buddha did with his... with his former teachers.
[SPEAKER_02]: They taught him these formless attainments and stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, you know, while he was in the training period, let's say, he was committed to that practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: And only then, when he wasn't like, oh no, I should be with this part.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, because of that, he actually got to experience exactly what the teachers were telling him to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: To the point that those teachers asked him to become a teacher as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, he said, but wait, this is not good enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you would have that that sense of... because you tried it, you would see, okay,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not because I did what I wanted and didn't listen to the doctor.
[SPEAKER_02]: I did exactly what he said, and yet I'm still not cured.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, at least you can tick that box.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, this doctor is not the right one.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you were following 10 doctors at once, like we said before, you're not any closer.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so that's confusing.
[SPEAKER_04]: And also, one slightly ironic thing with this attitude of picking and choosing is like,
[SPEAKER_04]: When you abandon that attitude, for example, and you stay with the suttas, and you discover how internally consistent, actually, a great many discourses are across the board, that's precisely a factor which increases faith.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you would never get that if you don't question that attitude of picking and choosing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And actually, the Buddha said in one discourse that
[SPEAKER_02]: At least at his time, he asked Ānanda, do you see even two monks in this assembly who have a different interpretation of the teaching?
[SPEAKER_02]: And he said, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the fact that you feel like you need to mix and pick and choose, yeah, you don't want to come to too quick conclusions about who's right and who's wrong, but you cannot
[SPEAKER_02]: Authentically and sincerely, allow yourself to think that all these people are in line with what the Buddha was teaching.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either... if they're teaching contradictory things, on that fundamental level, as the Buddha said, in regard to this discourse I just mentioned, it was about
[SPEAKER_02]: You see, any two monks who teach a different interpretation of the four satipaṭṭhānas, of the Noble Eightfold Path, of the four right strivings, of the five faculties, and you would see, even amidst, you know, teachers in the same tradition, you often have such very stark differences, but people kind of wave it away, hand wave it away, but saying, oh no, it's just...
[SPEAKER_02]: This is for people with certain tendency, and this is for people with another tendency.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not what the teacher is saying, though.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: He's saying everyone should be doing this.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, you're kind of allowing yourself to bend it into what you think.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's how quickly it goes.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you don't realize as well that, fundamentally, you cannot, like, escape your perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't just have, like, a perfectly objective point of view, where you're judging everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your standard for judging is your own view, which is what causes you suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's what's infected with ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: If you don't question it, you're not really growing in that sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: You kind of... Because another person... Why does this other person, who also claims to be following the Buddha's teaching, why is his mix so different from mine?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, I cannot honestly claim that we're both heading in the same direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's this kind of... yeah, inauthentic or shallow... shallow effort of reflection.
[SPEAKER_02]: Often because, again, it's not regarded as important a lot of the times.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, clarifying these sort of broader aspects is not that important.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just, just do the practice, just do the meditation, and then all these things just will magically, sort of, piece together.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's also faith, but about a naive one perhaps.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's, yeah, because it's, it's, it's not the faith that, um...
[SPEAKER_02]: That's leading to question yourself, as you said.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's kind of twisted.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, even then, you would have like a certain ideal of what you think nibbāna is, and you're kind of picking and choosing which practice will take me to that, instead of saying, wait, do I actually know what the goal is?
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's a type of faith that would push you back to that far, far background level, where you're going to be questioning everything from the ground up.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, because when you just start, you don't actually know what the goal is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or you might say... Because that's the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't see a cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you might say, well, the goal is to be free from suffering, but that doesn't necessarily mean that you've understood the full extent of suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: In fact, a Noble Disciple will have understood the full extent of suffering, because that's what's revealed with the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, that's how you get to see that... Well, without that faith, for example, oh, there's more to this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, many things that are actually just management of feelings, like feeling better, calmer, because you're managing, you wouldn't have, if you don't have faith, you wouldn't have the incisiveness to actually question and see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Actually, I'm still liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, it's a it's a it's something that
[SPEAKER_02]: Not necessarily you develop it directly, but you can certainly recognize in yourself a lack of faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, as the Buddha said, the conditions for faith, well...
[SPEAKER_02]: Reflect on... Do you actually feel a sense of urgency?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you actually feel, as the Buddha said, that... you know, for somebody who hasn't realized the Four Noble Truths, it's like they...
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, because what should somebody do if their head is on fire?
[SPEAKER_02]: He said they should apply unwavering effort, diligence, recollection, perseverance, in order to extinguish that fire.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he said, well, somebody might actually let the fire be, not pay attention to it, and it would actually be more important to make an effort to discern the four noble truths.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's obviously kind of a hyperbole in the sense, but it goes against a common kind of understanding that, oh, we just have to be satisfied with where you are right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you know,
[SPEAKER_02]: All these attainments and stuff, these are just more forms of becoming, and so it's more important to just accept yourself as you are now, and then just be with that, and that's how you... Just deal with it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the Buddha is saying you should see your situation as if your head is on fire.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so that's clearly a problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I wanted to maybe, like, briefly go back to, like, this kind of tendency of trying to find justification, like, with the teaching or with anything else, but in this context with the teaching, and I wanted to ask, like, someone can, like, listen to this discussion and say, okay, from now on, I will stop... make justification for myself, but that's kind of changing the things to, like, kind of an opinion level, but not yet to the view, so I wanted to ask, like,
[SPEAKER_03]: I think it will be kind of relevant to kind of make this distinction between like what an opinion, a belief is, and what the point of view is, because it's quite a different thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You mean, eh, justify, like, in terms of actions?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, it's when... the thing is, always then, if you have that attitude of
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, it's just... it's just this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just correct this and I'm already in the right path.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whichever shape that takes, if you don't assume, like, okay, I'm not justifying myself anymore, but do you stop there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you keep looking, like, okay, but... well, do I know the extent of action?
[SPEAKER_02]: For example, like, sure, I'm restraining my obvious
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, yeah, you accept, like, you have, like, an opinion of, yeah, I shouldn't act out of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's something that you can acquire in just a moment.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just read a book, it says, okay, don't do this, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But changing your view takes much longer, takes training, takes upgrading your criteria for what even... like the terms that you're using to begin with, like wholesome and wholesome, craving, abandoning, mind, consciousness,
[SPEAKER_02]: Are those... like, do you feel like that's it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or do you recognize, actually, even those things, I cannot be sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: I understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, when I'm saying...
[SPEAKER_02]: I am purifying my mind from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_02]: That might not mean for me what it should mean, for example.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's how you see that there is that extra dimension between you just accepting an opinion from something you read or something somebody told you, and then developing or adjusting your view according to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's that extra dimension of like
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, you agree with what they said, but how are you actually interpreting it internally?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, five aggregates, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a common example.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, people talk about the five aggregates, but they never stop to question the fact that maybe their definition of what five aggregates constitutes is either inaccurate or too vague or just overall not really referring to what the Buddha pointed to with these things.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what faith would allow you to consider, at least, that there's that constant improvement that needs to be made, constant questioning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even for a noble disciple, it's not a matter of just, okay, now I just mechanically do this practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Buddha said even, you cannot become an anāgāmī, so a sotāpanna would not be able to become an anāgāmī if they lack faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's... obviously, they have unshakable faith, but it can always be increased and deepened further.
[SPEAKER_02]: So...
[SPEAKER_02]: But, like I said, it's not something you increase directly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's through clarification.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, first, that sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I covering up the sense of urgency as well, through distractions and sensuality, which makes me feel like everything is all right, finding safety in the world?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's one way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, also, developing clarity.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's when, then, it's not just about faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: You also have to
[SPEAKER_02]: Clarify, for example, read the suttas, and clarify the teaching, so that it doesn't feel anymore like this vague, ambiguous, kind of, yes, I have to give a craving, but I don't really know what that means.
[SPEAKER_02]: You make it more, sort of, concrete, and then you get a sense of what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that increases your faith in a sense, because you see, oh wait, it's not even like this mystical.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you mystify things, and you make them kind of... put them too far away from you, then that's also not faith anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: It needs to be faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, it's over there, but I also have a recognition of what I can do.
[SPEAKER_02]: At least to bring me closer to that direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the Buddha called that measuring the task.
[SPEAKER_02]: You measure what it is that you actually need to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, on account of that, the faith, or you could say the desire, or the zeal to do it arises.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's a good point, because sometimes faith can be an excuse to do something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, I just have faith, which I'm practically not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what we're talking about is, the faith is precisely what ennobles you to go there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's not just, oh, this, nibbāna...
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and then the light in that faith, which is sometimes like devotion, but there can be an attitude of inauthenticity, just making excuses like, yeah, I have devotion, but practically you're not really doing anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, devotion can result from faith, but not the other way around, necessarily.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, because you would still see, you know, in the suttas, like how the monks would be, even when they were arahants, they would say, like, somebody would come and ask them a question,
[SPEAKER_02]: And, eh... they would say... well, you shouldn't ask me.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not the one who knows.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the teacher.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's... the Buddha is the one who knows.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, eh... even though they were arahants.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you could see that, yes, there was a sense of devotion there.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you just fabricate that...
[SPEAKER_02]: It really makes sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just hollow, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But perhaps it can also be helpful to clarify a bit, like, in order to, like, find a starting point.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, faith in the suttas, even with the Buddha, it is like seeing a dead person just in the streets, somebody who is old or sick.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is what, for the Buddha,
[SPEAKER_04]: Kindled that search, that faith.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, suffering is not like, oh, I have particular problems, like my child is misbehaving, or my marriage is going down the drain.
[SPEAKER_04]: These are all particular things.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure, that's all unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: But actually, that faith is on the level, as we said earlier, of past existence.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, even if everything is now going according to your wishes,
[SPEAKER_04]: You're still subject to old age, sickness, death.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is where the hair is on fire.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that faith, in its nature, covers
[SPEAKER_04]: The whole of your life, it's not this particular situation or this particular problem that is now occupying your mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's much bigger picture.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's why we said it would have to have an effect on the way you live your life, if it's genuine faith.
[SPEAKER_04]: It cannot just remain as an empty conviction.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so people can ask, is the fact that I'm subjected to all day sickness, death, genuinely a problem for me?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if somebody then thinks, well, this is the only life I just try to live, to sit out of it as comfortably as possible, and then that's it, that's going to be an obstruction to faith as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you'd be surprised how many Buddhists kind of have that view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, it's, it's, oh, well, you know, it's, it's, eh, I'll just do the best in this life, and then, eh, whether they believe in rebirth or not, they might say, oh, well, I'll just
[SPEAKER_02]: Get reborn in the next one and do my best and... Then I'll do the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like right now I have family, I have children.
[SPEAKER_02]: I cannot do it right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll do it later.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, yeah, that means... Sure, you still recognize the value in an ambiguous sense of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I like to compare that to like somebody who, let's say, they already earn a hundred thousand per year.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, they have the option to gain one million.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, sure, I would like to do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, if it takes too much of my effort and too much of my energy, I might just rest comfortable with what I already have.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, that's kind of the interpretation that a lot of people have behind like stream entry and all these things.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, it's not something that you're gaining.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a huge problem that you need to lose.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's your head being on fire.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you see it in that way, that's not something that you can just kick your legs up and say, okay, I'll just stay with my head on fire.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if it doesn't feel like that kind of
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, basically, there isn't anything else, really, that's worth it, apart from this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you haven't recognized sufficiently the perilous situation that saṃsāra is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, with the proper faith, you cannot say, I'm doing this practice, but there's also something of equal importance next to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That cannot be.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.